Presidential and Inaugural Collection
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Presidential and Inaugural Collection 1835-2021 1944-2021
MSS3449
200 items
2 containers
0.8 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Correspondence, etiquette and protocol information cards, invitations, memorabilia, menu cards, photographs, programs, seating plans, tickets, and other ephemera relating to presidential inaugurations and presidents.
Acquisition Information
The Presidential and Inaugural Collection was acquired by the Library of Congress from various sources.
Access and Restrictions
The Presidential and Inaugural Collection is open to research. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting.
Scope and Content Note
The Presidential and Inaugural Collection spans the years 1835-2021, with the bulk of the material dating from 1944 to 2021. The collection primarily documents presidential inaugurations and the events that have historically surrounded them, including balls and dinners, but the collection is not inclusive of every presidential inauguration. The collection includes commemorative presidential inauguration buttons, cutouts of candidates' faces, COVID-19 face masks from the 2021 inauguration, a Metrorail pass, programs, and tickets, as well as invitations to balls, lunches, and other official events staged by the Joint Congressional Committee on Inaugural Ceremonies. The Washington Assemblies file includes invitations to balls celebrating George Washington's birthday.
The Kathleen D. Harney files pertain to her time serving as chief of the White House Press Releases Office, during four presidential administrations between 1944 and 1967. Harney worked in the White House library where she was in charge of press release files, and organized and maintained presidential statements. Her files contain Christmas cards, commemorative programs, correspondence, invitations, photographs, and other ephemera.
Arrangement of the Collection
This collection is arranged with the Washington Assemblies file first followed by Kathleen D. Harney's files. The remaining files are arranged chronologically by inauguration.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Harney, Kathleen D. Kathleen D. Harney papers. 1944-1970.; Washington, George, 1732-1799--Anniversaries, etc.
Organizations
United States. Congress. Joint Congressional Committee on Inaugural Ceremonies.
Subjects
COVID-19 Pandemic, 2020---Social aspects--United States.; Inauguration Day.; Presidents--United States--Inauguration.; Presidents--United States.
Places
Washington (D.C.)--Social life and customs.
Container List
- Washington Assemblies, 1835-1843 (Box 1)
- Harney, Kathleen D., 1944-1970, (2 folders) (Box 1)
- Inaugural events (Box 1)
  - 1841, Harrison, William Henry (Box 1)
  - 1849, Taylor, Zachary (Box 1)
  - 1857, Buchanan, James (Box 1)
  - 1865, Lincoln, Abraham (Box 1)
  - 1893, Cleveland, Grover (Box 1)
  - 1897-1901, McKinley, William (Box 1)
  - 1909, Taft, William H. (Box 1)
  - 1933-1941, Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Box 1)
  - 1949, Truman, Harry S. (Box 1)
  - 1953-1957, Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Box 1)
  - 1961, Kennedy, John F. (Box 1)
  - 1965, Johnson, Lyndon B. (Box 1)
  - 1969, Nixon, Richard M. (Box 1)
  - 1973, Nixon, Richard M. (Box 2)
  - 2001, Bush, George W. (Box 2)
  - 2009, Obama, Barack (Box 2)
  - 2017, Trump, Donald, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - 2021, Biden, Joseph R., Jr. (Box 2)